{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This event killed the inspirational author Elbert Hubbard. William Thomas Turner was criticized after this event for ignoring orders to maintain a zig-zag course off the Old Head of Kinsale. William Jennings Bryan resigned as Secretary of State in protest to Woodrow Wilson's response to this event, which prompted debate about a vessel's status as a legitimate military target. For 10 points, name this May 1915 event in which a British ocean liner was sunk by a U- boat.",
      "answer": "sinking of the RMS Lusitania <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This king earned his country land in the Treaty of Stolbovo, which ended the Ingrian War against Russia. He continued a war that his father Charles IX started with Polish king Sigismund III. This leader scored a decisive victory against the Count of Tilly at Breitenfeld. While leading a cavalry charge, this king died at the Battle of Lutzen. For 10 points, name this \"Lion of the North,\" a Swedish king who fought in the Thirty Years' War.",
      "answer": "Gustavus Adolphus <JL> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Each year at this location, Aladdin the Christmas Camel recreates a show put on by this place's owner. Louise and Ann Cunningham were horrified to see this place in poor condition and formed a Ladies' Association to repair it. The owner of this place acquired a severe sore throat in the winter and was advised excessive bloodletting by his personal physicians, which helped kill him. For 10 points, name this Virginia plantation home of George Washington.",
      "answer": "Mount Vernon <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This island was once home to the Beothuk people. The protagonist of The Shipping News by E. Annie Proulx (pr. PROOL) returns to this island. The first transatlantic wireless message traveled from England to this island's Signal Hill. This island is home to a former Viking settlement at L'Anse aux Meadows (pr. LONS-oh Meadows). The capital of the most recently incorporated Canadian province is this island's city of St. John's. For 10 points, name this island that composes a province with Labrador.",
      "answer": "Newfoundland <KG> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two days before this event, a look alike named Felix Dadaev (pr. duh-DYE-ev) was told to \"be ready to stand in\" if needed. Jonathan Brent and Vladimir Naumov theorized that a secret police chief caused this event by slipping warfarin into a man's wine glass. It set up a power struggle featuring such men as Lavrenty Beria and former Foreign Affairs Minister Molotov, who both failed in their attempts to take over. For 10 points, name this 1953 death of a Soviet leader.",
      "answer": [
        "The death of Joseph Stalin ,",
        "just “Stalin” after “death” <MC> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 4"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This non-Christian deity is Vasco da Gama's main supernatural helper in the Portuguese epic, the Lusiads. In Ovid's Metamorphoses, this deity begs Jupiter to turn the murdered Julius Caesar into a star, since the historical Julii (pr. JOO-lee-ee) clan claimed descent from her. In another foundation myth, she presents a shield depicting future Roman history to her son, which she had requested from her husband Vulcan. For 10 points, name this mother of Aeneas, the Roman goddess of love.",
      "answer": "Venus <MJ> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "The president of the country targeted by this event delayed negotiations by traveling to Mauritius. Following this event, Dora Bloch was killed at a hospital. Two members of the German Revolutionary Cells assisted in a hijacking ordered by Wadie Haddad that occurred a week before this event. Benjamin Netanyahu's brother Yonatan was killed during this event. For 10 points, identify this 1976 event in which Israeli forces rescued hostages from Uganda.",
      "answer": "Entebbe Raid <KG> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man called Maya Lin an “egg roll” during the competition to design the Vietnam Memorial. This man sponsored a group led by Arthur D. Simons, which rescued two employees of his company, Electronic Data Systems. During one speech, he urged his audience to listen for the “giant sucking sound” caused by the signing of NAFTA. For 10 points, name his founder of the Reform Party and businessman who ran in the 1992 and 1996 presidential elections.",
      "answer": "Henry Ross Perot <EM> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 4"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The last person to take a photo of this object in its entirety was Jack Schmidtt, who was accompanied by Eugene Cernan and Ronald Evans. Carl Sagan titled the sequel to Cosmos for a photograph of this object. Another photograph taken by Bill Anders of this object is titled for its \"rise,\" and was taken during the first manned mission to orbit the moon. For 10 points, name this object photographed by Voyager 1 in \"Pale Blue Dot\" and by Apollo 17 in \"The Blue Marble.\"",
        "answer": "photographs of Earth"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A \"Family Portrait\" photograph of six out of eight planets was taken by the MESSENGER probe, which was sent to which planet?",
        "answer": "Mercury <VP>"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Pierce Patent made this document no longer necessary. This document was most likely written by William Brewster and was intended to settle differences between the \"Strangers\" and the \"Saints.\" Although its original is lost, it was copied in William Bradford's journal and reprinted in Of Plymouth Plantation. For 10 points, what 1620 document established a \"civil body politic\" out of the group that had come to America on the namesake ship?",
        "answer": "Mayflower Compact"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What military advisor to the Plymouth Colony captured the colony of Merrymount?",
        "answer": "Myles Standish <DW> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was preceded by the Address of the 221. It was prompted by the publishing in “Le Moniteur” of the Ordinances of St. Cloud, which dissolved the Chamber of Deputies. An appeal to Jules de Polignac (pr. pole-en-YACK) failed during this event, which took place during the “Three Glorious Days.” It saw the capture of the Hotel de Ville and the creation of barricades. For 10 points, name this event in France which saw replacement of Charles X with Louis Philippe.",
        "answer": "July Revolution"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Belgian Revolution and July Revolution both occurred in which year?",
        "answer": "1830 <JZ> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This novel's second volume ends with a great comet overhead, which reminds the protagonist of the number 666. This novel's Second Epilogue restates its many digressions claiming that the course of history does not depend on great men. In this novel, Prince Andrei serves in the army under General Kutuzov, who burns Moscow shortly before Pierre Bezukhov is taken prisoner in 1812. For 10 points, name this long novel about Napoleon's invasion of Russia, by Leo Tolstoy.",
        "answer": "War and Peace"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other Russian literary character, created by Fyodor Dostoevsky, tells Sonia he \"wanted to become a Napoleon\" after murdering a pawnbroker?",
        "answer": "Rodion Romanovich Raskolnikov <MJ> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 4"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a victory for this commander, his forces ambushed and pinned down those of Flaminius next to a body of water. The Fabian strategy was first employed to slow this man's advances. After entering Italy, this general led forces to victory in the battles of Trebia and Lake Trasimene. This general's elephants were neutralized in a plan by Scipio Africanus that helped lead to his defeat at the Battle of Zama. For 10 points, name this Carthaginian general.",
        "answer": "Hannibal Barca"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another of Hannibal's victories was at what battle, in which he defeated a numerically superior Roman force led by Varro and Paullus through a pincer movement?",
        "answer": "Battle of Cannae <JL> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Supporters of this group wore football helmets while vandalizing the Gold Coast neighborhood. This group held the Flint War Council after organizing an attempt to \"bring the war home,\" the Days of Rage. Three members of this group were killed while making a nail bomb in Greenwich Village. This group took its name from a Bob Dylan lyric about \"which way the wind blows.\" For 10 points, name this militant left-wing group which operated during the Vietnam War.",
        "answer": "Weathermen"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Weathermen were a radical splinter of what student group, whose Port Huron statement was drafted by Tom Hayden?",
        "answer": "Students for a Democratic Society <JB> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader's ministers argued over whether to launch a punitive invasion in the Seikanron debate. This leader promoted the slogan \"enrich the country, strengthen the military\" in place of the earlier sonno joi idea. Saigo Takamori rebelled against this leader in the Satsuma War, and this leader came to power by winning the Boshin War. For 10 points, name this westernizing Japanese emperor who ended the Tokugawa shogunate.",
        "answer": "Meiji Emperor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The goals of the Meiji Restoration were outlined in what five article document?",
        "answer": "Charter Oath <JB> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This policy was partly a response to the concept of Calvo clauses and to the Drago Doctrine. This policy was announced after a crisis in which Cipriano Castro refused to pay his country's debts. The Clark Memorandum repudiated this doctrine, which was replaced by the Good Neighbor Policy. For 10 points, name this key part of the \"big stick\" policy, an addition to the Monroe Doctrine proposed by Teddy Roosevelt.",
        "answer": "Roosevelt Corollary to the Monroe Doctrine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In his speech introducing the Corollary, Roosevelt praised what amendment, which replaced the Teller Amendment and allowed U.S. intervention in Cuban affairs?",
        "answer": "Platt Amendment <JB> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 4"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "GOING TO COLLEGE",
      "prompt": "Which American college or university...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Located in Washington, DC is named after the first President of the United States?",
          "answer": "George Washington University"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was founded in 1636 as America’s first university?",
          "answer": "Harvard"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a protest against the Vietnam War in which four people were killed?",
          "answer": "Kent State University"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a “Prison Experiment” conducted by Philip Zimbardo?",
          "answer": "Stanford University"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was founded by Thomas Jefferson in 1819?",
          "answer": "University of Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was home to the first PhD program in anthropology headed by Franz Boas?",
          "answer": "Columbia University"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was formerly presided over by virologist David Baltimore and employed Richard Feynman?",
          "answer": "Caltech"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to the first medical school in the United States, whose faculty included Benjamin Rush?",
          "answer": "University of Pennsylvania <EM> {I}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "NAPOLEON BONAPARTE",
      "prompt": "Name the napoleon bonaparte...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the Emperor of what nation?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unsuccessfully invaded what nation, then led by Alexander I?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lost to Horatio Nelson at what 1805 naval battle?",
          "answer": "Battle of Trafalgar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fought the Peninsular War when trying to install his brother on what country’s throne?",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Used what program to impose a trade embargo on Britain?",
          "answer": "Continental System"
        },
        {
          "question": "Destroyed what empire, led by Francis II, in the Treaty of Pressburg?",
          "answer": "Holy Roman Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed the Concordat of 1801 with and was crowned by what Pope?",
          "answer": "Pius VII"
        },
        {
          "question": "Won what 1797 battle in Italy during the Siege of Mantua against Jozsef Alvinczi?",
          "answer": "Battle of Rivoli <JZ> {I}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "LITERATURE OF WORLD WAR II",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about LITERATURE OF WORLD WAR II...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "is the setting of what Holocaust’s victim The Diary of a Young Girl?",
          "answer": "Annelies Marie “Anne” Frank"
        },
        {
          "question": "was distantly sparked by what leader’s manifesto Mein Kampf?",
          "answer": "Adolf Hitler"
        },
        {
          "question": "is fictionalized in The Moon is Down, a novel by what author of Of Mice and Men?",
          "answer": "John Steinbeck Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "is satirized in what Joseph Heller novel set on Pianosa?",
          "answer": "Catch-22"
        },
        {
          "question": "figures into what postmodern novel about the sexual conquests of Tyrone Slothrop?",
          "answer": "Gravity’s Rainbow"
        },
        {
          "question": "forms the backdrop of a Kurt Vonnegut novel in which what man gets unstuck in time?",
          "answer": "Billy Pilgrim"
        },
        {
          "question": "was when Joe Keller manufactured faulty airplane parts in what 1947 play?",
          "answer": "All My Sons"
        },
        {
          "question": "led to what journalist’s article Hiroshima?",
          "answer": "John Hersey <Ike> {I}"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Tsar Paul sheltered many members of this group in 1798, and got them to declare him their leader rather than Ferdinand von Hompesch. This group, led early on by Raymond de Puy, began around a building founded by Amalfi merchants. Pope (20 pts)",
        "Paschal II formally recognized this group, which was led by Jean de Valette after it relocated to Malta from the Suleiman-besieged island of (10 pts)",
        "Rhodes. Formally, its members venerated the man who baptized Jesus. For 10 points, name this non-Templar Crusader order founded to protect centers for healing the wounded."
      ],
      "answer": "Knights Hospitalers <MJ> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man claimed an enemy moved \"with the perseverance of a mighty avalanche.\" This man was defended by Francis Scott Key after he assaulted Congressman William Stanberry. He suffered a bullet wound in his ankle prior to the signing of the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Velasco. The only man to be elected governor of two different U.S. states, he was also the only Southern governor to oppose (10 pts)",
        "secession. He was succeeded as President by Mirabeau Lamar. For 10 points, name this first President of the Republic of Texas and namesake of the state's most populous city."
      ],
      "answer": "Samuel “Sam” Houston <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man co-founded the micronation of Nutopia in response to the Nixon administration’s efforts to deport him. This man gave an interview with him and his wife entirely covered in a bag as a political statement. He sang “we gave her everything we owned just to sit at her (20 pts)",
        "table” in a song critical of the Maharishi, “Sexy Sadie.” During his honeymoon, he staged a “bed-in” in protest of the (10 pts)",
        "Vietnam War, and he was murdered three weeks after releasing Double Fantasy by a man upset that he once called his band “bigger than Jesus,” Mark David Chapman. For 10 points, name this Beatle who married Yoko Ono and sang “Imagine.”"
      ],
      "answer": "John Lennon <CW> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This policy was partly inspired by a volcanic eruption on Thera and the use of the Hodegetria during a siege. Opponents of this policy claimed that a king had defecated in his baptismal font, earning him the epithet \"copronymus.\" Riots over this policy began with an action at the Chalke gate. This policy was supported by the (20 pts)",
        "Council of Hieria, but condemned by the Second Council of Nicaea (pr. nigh-SEE-uh), which was called by (10 pts)",
        "Irene. This policy was begun by Leo III of the Isaurian dynasty. For 10 points, name this policy which called for the destruction of Byzantine religious images."
      ],
      "answer": "Byzantine iconoclasm <JB> 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 4"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician remarked: “This is not cojones (pr. co-HO-nace). This is cowardice” after Cuban pilots shot down two planes flown by Brothers to the Rescue. This politician articulated the “three Ds of NATO” and sparred with Boutros Boutros-Ghali as (20 pts)",
        "ambassador to the UN. This Czechoslovak-born politician succeeded Warren Christopher and preceded (10 pts)",
        "Colin Powell in an office in whose tenure she made a high-profile visit to North Korea to meet with Kim Jong-Il. For 10 points, name this first female Secretary of State, a member of President Bill Clinton’s Cabinet."
      ],
      "answer": "Madeleine Albright <AG> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist painted several depictions of a hunter and his dog in the first of his tapestry cartoons. This artist created multiple works in which dismembered body parts are stuck on tree branches, and others in which soldiers attempt to sexually assault women. Another of his works shows a diagonal line of hatted (20 pts)",
        "soldiers standing near a box lantern that casts light on the central figure. This creator of the Disasters of War etching series also (10 pts)",
        "unflatteringly painted his patron, Charles IV of Spain. For 10 points, name this creator of a painting in which a man assumes a Christ-like pose in front of a firing squad on The 3rd of May, 1808."
      ],
      "answer": "Francisco Jose de Goya y Lucientes <AK> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Following one of these events, the emissary Suh Chan was beheaded. During one of these events, Hong Dagu chose to attack before reinforcements traveling from Zhousan Island arrived. Fan Wenhu and much of a defeated Song army was pressed into service for the (20 pts)",
        "second of these conflicts. A series of scrolls about these conflicts, commissioned by Takezaki Suenaga, included a depiction of a (10 pts)",
        "landing on northern Kyushu. For 10 points, what 1274 and 1281 invasions were stopped by typhoons known as kamikaze?"
      ],
      "answer": "Mongol invasions of Japan <DW> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Carles Haughey’s photographs of this conflict are collected in “A Weather Walked in”. In one image of this conflict, a man with a plaid shirt and his arms behind his back has a (20 pts)",
        "gun pointed at his head Nick Ut took a Pulitzer-winning photograph of this war in which five small (10 pts)",
        "children, one a completely naked girl, run down a road towards the viewer as smoke rises in the background. Early in this war, Malcolm Browne took a picture of a monk burning himself to protest Ngo Dinh Diem's crackdown on Buddhists. For 10 points, name this war whose end led to photographs of American helicopters leaving a country reunified under Communism."
      ],
      "answer": "Vietnam War <MJ> 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 4"
    }
  ]
}